<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wip | Achu Wilson</title>
    <link>https://achuwilson.github.io/tags/wip/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://achuwilson.github.io/tags/wip/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>wip</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Achu Wilson 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://achuwilson.github.io/img/pom-card.png</url>
      <title>wip</title>
      <link>https://achuwilson.github.io/tags/wip/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonprehensile Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2021-edgepivot/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2021-edgepivot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;DIV align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#how&#34;&gt;How&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans can manipulate objects in interesting ways without even grasping them. We make use of the properties of the object as well as the environment to push, flip, throw and squeeze objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows a human hand pushing a paper box on a table and pivoting it around an edge. We can do such a task just by relying on the forces felt on the finger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;handdemo.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://manipulation.csail.mit.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MIT 6.881 Manipulation class&lt;/a&gt; Fall 2020, which was offered entirely online, had a class project and I decided to try this. A Kuka LBR iiwa robot, fitted with a simple single finger end effector is used to achieve the task. The robot does not have the model of the object nor the environment (No prior knowledge of the dimensions of the box or the position coordinates of the edge). The workspace limitations of the robot restrict moving the object under the table, but the method could be extended for any such capable robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the model of the object and environment is not provided and no external vision sensors are used, proprioceptive data alone is to be used. The joint torques and position from the robot are used in combination with the impedance control capabilities of the iiwa to estimate the model parameters. This would be an almost impossible or incredibly difficult task with a conventional position-controlled stiff robot, even if equipped with a Force/Torque sensor. The entire system is implemented in Drake as a state machine. The following paragraphs detail the approach used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the robot moves at a constant velocity in the negative z-axis. Individual joint velocities are calculated from the desired velocity using a PsuedoInverseJacobian controller. Since the iiwa does not have a joint velocity input, the computed joint velocities are integrated to obtain the joint position inputs.
&lt;img src=&#34;push0.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
While the robot is moving at such a constant velocity, the force on the end effector is being monitored. IIWA provides joint torques estimated at the 7 joints. The external wrench at the end effector is calculated using the PsuedoInverseJacobian method. When the z-axis force is above an experimentally determined threshold, the state machine jumps into the next state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the finger touches the box, it applies a downward force and a forward velocity such that the resultant force is outside the friction cone of the contact between the box and table. Since the friction coefficient is unknown, the forces are determined experimentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Drake Kuka driver allows us to provide a feedforward torque to each joint. The individual feedforward torque values are calculated from the desired end-effector wrench using the Jacobian transpose methods and commanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;push1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the finger approaches the edge of the table, interesting things start to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;push2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the center of gravity moves past the edge, the gravitational force acting on it causes a torque centered around the edge. This torque generates an upwards force on the fingers (green up arrows). Since the iiwa operates in impedance control mode, it is not very stiff in the z-axis. So, it deviates minutely from the previous positions in the vertical direction, moving in an arc centered around the corner. The derivative of z-axis force is used to detect the beginning of this deviation and is used to transition the state machine to the next state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the box starts pivoting, the finger continues moving in the x-axis, until the vertical z-axis reaction force generated by the box on the finger is zero. The gravitational force on the object would be balanced by the horizontal component of the forces on the finger and the corner. The motion of the finger is stopped and any incremental motion will cause the object to fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;push3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following plot shows the z axis finger coordinates during this time and we can clearly see the arc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;data2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following graph shows the forces and their derivatives on the finger until the box is balanced between the finger and the corner (T3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;data1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From 0 to T1, the finger moves down at the constant velocity. The force readings are quite noisy when the finger is not in contact with anything and the accuracy is only +/-5N.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spike at T1 is caused by contact with the object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From T1 to T2, The finger moves towards the edge, applying a constant force in the z-axis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At T2, the box starts pivoting due to torque induced by gravity. the derivative of the force is found to be a reliable estimate to detect this rather than the raw noisy force data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From T1 to T3, the z-axis force peaks and then drops. It is this force that causes the compliant z-axis to deviate in position and move in an arc, which is shown in the plot of pZ (z-axis position).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At T3, the box is balanced perfectly between the finger and the corner. The force on the z-axis drops while the x-axis force increases. The motion of the finger is stopped at this point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The points on the arc are observed and fitted onto a model of the circle to estimate the model parameters: the position coordinate of the corner and the size of the object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;push4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we estimate the center and radius from the arc, we plan a trajectory along the perimeter, starting from the current finger position and finishing at a position when the box is vertical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;push5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trajectory includes the positions of each frame (blue dots) as well as the forces (green arrows) at all these frames. This makes sure that while pivoting, the vector sum of forces direct towards the corner position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robot then moves along the trajectory.
&lt;img src=&#34;push6.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the finger reaches the end of the above trajectory, a new trajectory is planned, along the same path to pivot the box back to the horizontal position. While executing this new trajectory, fingers move along the circular path, with tangential velocity and radial force components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the box is nearly vertical, the state machine transitions into a new state, in which the finger moves a little up or down to maintain a pre-determined vertical force on the box. This accounts for the accumulated position errors caused during the estimation of the model parameters. Once it is done, the state machine transitions it to the final state where the finger moves horizontally, moving the box to the initial position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video (3x sped up) shows the system in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hlw0aVvvHLQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The approach works reliably and is tested with boxes of different sizes and weights as well as for different table positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following areas could be improved for better performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The system cannot detect the slip that might occur. A tactile sensorized finger (GelSight?) could be used for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The joint torques reported by iiwa are not very accurate and are also pose dependant. This could be improved using an external F/T sensor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The estimated model may not be always perfectly accurate. The inaccuracy in the estimated edge position causes a jerking motion when we start applying force towards the center.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The finger position not only depends on the commanded position but the feed-forward torque also, this makes the transition between feed-forward torque control mode and trajectory execution mode tricky and causes little jerks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In-Hand Rolling</title>
      <link>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2020-in-hand-rolling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2020-in-hand-rolling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;DIV align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#previous-works&#34;&gt;Previous works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#going-further&#34;&gt;Going Further&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite recent and an exploratory side project to explore classification of visually similar yet physical objects. The best example would be geodesic polyhedrons of different frequencies, which can trick visual - both color and depth systems as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;rgb-depth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surface geometry of the object could be estimated using a robot gripper which has a GelSight sensor. A CNN using MobileNet architecture  was trained to classify the objectsfrom the raw GelSight data. It worked pretty good (~90% accuracy) on the test objects. Analyzing the false classifications indicated that the tactile data may not be perfect during all the grasps. We humans also gets confused in the same way occasionally, if we grab objects with just two fingers. We would then either proceed to close the fingers to make more contact surface area with the object or roll the object between our fingers as in the following video to classify it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;handroll.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would then give us more tactile data and increases our belief probability. This work involves exploring whether such a capability can improve tactile sensing for robots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-works&#34;&gt;Previous Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much research has been done in tactile object recognition as well as in hand manipulation
&lt;a href=&#34;https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/77000058.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7363508&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike those approaches. this work explores on learning a finger movement repertoire, that could maximize the in-hand object recognition/localization capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows the prototype gripper classifying two test objects (geodesic spheres with hexagonal and triangular faces, that can be better felt by touch)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1bOfoukle06T8DrrSyyc8ingNUB5qe8He/preview&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; align =&#34;center&#34; &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that it falsely classifies objects once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A modular 3rd axis is inserted in between the finger and the gripper, which can rotate the object in hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1L_x2ZVm-HVFxSDLjEirT3ZcQ40vBXKNi/preview&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classification probabilities during this motion are averaged to get a more accurate estimate of the object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note: it has been tested only with symmetric objects, which are easy to roll and is still an ongoing project)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-further&#34;&gt;Going Further&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More experimentation, primarily on the following would be explored as time permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3D reconstruction using techniques using ICP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recursive Neural network to extract temporal data during rolling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BlindGrasp</title>
      <link>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2020-blindgrasp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2020-blindgrasp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;DIV align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#previous-works&#34;&gt;Previous works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#how&#34;&gt;How&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlindGrasp, as the name implies, aims at grasping objects when the robot&amp;rsquo;s eyes are blindfolded. This idea had been lingering in my mind, ever since I came across the GelSight optical tactile sensor. It is a tough and challenging problem and I have been making slow, yet good progress. This is the main project that I am spending my time now and has helped us to be the finalist in the &lt;em&gt;Kuka Innovation Award 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans have excellent grasping capabilities in unstructured environments which are still unmatched by robots. This can be attributed to the dexterous human hand, robust visual and tactile sensing capabilities as well as to the intelligent brain which makes conscious and subconscious decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual sensing is traditionally used extensively in robotics when compared to tactile sensing. Tactile sensing is harder, mainly due to the difficulty in interpreting and making sense of the complex tactile signals. The recent developments in machine learning - particularly Deep Reinforcement Learning has opened new possibilities in the making usage of such complex data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We humans can effortlessly put a hand inside a bag, search by moving it around and pick up an item or we can use our hands to dig or sieve through granular medium like sand and pick up an object. This project explores building a system which learns manipulation and grasping skills in such vision denied environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-works&#34;&gt;Previous Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grasping objects, using tactile sensing alone as well as in granular media are explored more recently. Following are some of the early works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robotics.stanford.edu/~ang/papers/icra09-ProximityGrasping.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reactive Grasping Using Optical Proximity Sensors&lt;/a&gt; by Kaijen Hsaio et al.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://choice.umn.edu/deep-learning-approach-grasping-invisible&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Deep Learning Approach to Grasping the Invisible&lt;/a&gt;, by Yang Yang et al.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/9158928&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vibro-Tactile Foreign Body Detection in Granular Objects based on Squeeze-Induced Mechanical Vibrations&lt;/a&gt; by Togzhan Syrymova et al.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1909.04787&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MAT: Multi-Fingered Adaptive Tactile Grasping via Deep Reinforcement Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Bohan Wu et al.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1805.04201&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Learning to Grasp without Seeing&lt;/a&gt; by Adithyavairavan Murali et al.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Multimodal Haptic Perception within Granular Media via Recurrent Neural Networks&lt;/a&gt; by S.Jia et al.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are almost no works combining tactile sensing- exploration and grasping objects in granular media&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bringing such novel manipulation capabilities to robots calls for better robot hands as well as algorithms. The stated goals of the project are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a novel tactile sensing capable gripper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop AI techniques to make the robot learn how to explore, detect and grasp objects in unstructured-vision denied environments where tactile sensing only could be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tactile Sensing Gripper consists of a two finger parallel jaw gripper, with tactile sensing capabilities. Similar to the human fingers, the inner surface of the fingers would be having a high spatial resolution tactile sensing capability and the outer surface comparatively lower resolution. The highly sensitive inner surface of the finger helps in recognizing objects from their shape, texture as well as in fine manipulation skills. The lower sensitive outer surface helps in detecting the presence of nearby objects via contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI System consists of a Deep Reinforcement Learning Agent that learns how to explore the environment and to recognize/differentiate objects and pick them up. The agent uses data from the two types of tactile sensors on each of the fingers, proprioception and force sensor data from the robot arm. The agent decides the direction of motion of the end effector and the control of the gripper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a relatively simple task to start with, grasping specific objects from an environment similar to the following setup will have to be acheived using the tactile sensing alone.&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;img src=&#34;https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2020-blindgrasp/pick1_hu5216c571185a4b1be355b78cbb1a0511_203481_450x450_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; width=&#34;415&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; alt=&#34;picking task 1&#34;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the robot is expected to learn how to pick up objects under the granular media as in the following simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a2rk8dN3KsA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A novel gripper, with tactile sensing around the finger is built and we are collecting data from the real world environment. This would be augmented with data from the simulated environment and human demonstrations to train the RL agent for the task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More updates coming soon, as it is an ongoing project..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chero</title>
      <link>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2019-chero/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://achuwilson.github.io/project/2019-chero/</guid>
      <description>&lt;DIV align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#previous-works&#34;&gt;Previous works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#what-makes-it-special&#34;&gt;What makes it special&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#going-further&#34;&gt;Going Further&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-and-why&#34;&gt;What and Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chero is my acronym for  Chef-Robot, an ongoing project motivated by my desire to have a personal robot arm to experiment with. My long term dream of such a robot was triggered into action by the  MIT Collaborative Intelligence Challenge 2019, in which I gave a try. In addition, it as an interesting challenge and learning oppertunity to build such a system from grounds up - mechanical design-electronics controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-works&#34;&gt;Previous Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Direct drive robots are, as the name implies, are robots in which the motors directly drive the shaft without using a gearbox. It was introduced by Asada et al as early as early 80s 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ri.cmu.edu/pub_files/pub4/asada_haruhiko_1981_1/asada_haruhiko_1981_1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/direct-drive-robots&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Direct drive robots have many inherent advantages like better torque control, dynamic response, zero backlash and friction etc. Despite all these advantages, the main disadvantage that prevented direct drive robots from becoming mainstream is mainly the low torque density of electrical motors. However, recent advancements in technology has brought us high torque BLDC motors, which are used either used directly or in combination with a  low gear ratio (&amp;lt;10) reducer. Notable robots include berkeley openarms
&lt;a href=&#34;https://berkeleyopenarms.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;,   and numerous quadrupeds like MIT Cheetah 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6631038&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; and works by Gavin Kenneally et al
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7403902&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-makes-it-special&#34;&gt;What makes it special&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quasi-Direct Drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spherical shoulder and wrist joints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redundant Robot - 7DOF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheap and affordable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Quasi- Direct drive system consists of timing belt driven axes with a reduction ratio of 3. High torque density gimbal BLDC motors are used to actuate these joints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robot also has spherical joints at both the shoulder and the wrist, which matches closely with human arms.  It is shown that such a wrist design can be quite helpful in dexterous manipulation applications 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8624352&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design is almost complete, parts machined-3dprinted and a video of first 4 DOF can be seen below

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/R1Q4KODC1f4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 3DOF spherical wrist is also designed and assembled. It will be attached soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-further&#34;&gt;Going Further&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementing controllers, integrating with Drake&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
